Guide to the American Theological Library Association Library Development Program Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
American Theological Library Association Library Development Program Records
1960-1973
RG 81
Yale University Divinity School Library
7
(15 boxes)
The records include correspondence, reports, and financial records related to the ATLA Library Development Program. The ATLA Library Development Program provided funds to strengthen the book collections of ninety North American theological libraries between 1961 and 1966. The program was directed by Raymond Morris, Librarian of the Yale Divinity School Library and funded by the Sealantic Fund.
American Theological Library Association
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Deposited by the ATLA
Biographical / Historical
The primary objective of the Library Development Program of the American Theological Library Association was to strengthen book collections in North American theological libraries by enabling them to increase their book purchases. With the support of The Sealantic Fund, Inc., the Library Development Program provided more than $1,300,000 in book and related funds to ninety participating institutions during the period 1961 to 1966.
Each institution participating in the Library Development Program was challenged to increase its average annual book budget by as much as $3000. Whatever the library spent in excess of its normal budget was matched by funds from The Sealantic Fund. Emphasis was placed on standards of quality and discrimination in book acquisition, as well as on effectiveness in library service. Each library was encouraged to engage in a critical analysis of its own services. In addition, the Library Development Program (LDP) made visitation teams available. The role of these teams was to spend a period of time at an institution and provide outside assessment of the quality of the library facilities and services. A total of sixty-nine institutions were visited by LDP teams.
The Library Development Program operated out of the office of Dr., Raymond P. Morris, who was Librarian of the Yale Divinity School at the time, and chairman of the LDP. A Theological Book List was compiled by Dr. Morris to assist participating institutions in assessing their book holdings, and a Self-Study Guide was prepared to assist in library evaluation.
Additional information about the procedures and results of the Library Development Program is available in nineteen bulletins issued by its administrative office, contained in Box 1, Folder 1 of the collection.
Scope and Contents
Series I contains documents and correspondence which relate to the general operations of the LDP. The bulk of the collection falls in Series II, which is arranged alphabetically by institution. The material for each institution is chronologically arranged within two formats: reports/forms and correspondence. Series III contains correspondence, reports and record books documenting the financial operations of the Library Development Program.
Arrangement
I. Administrative Material
II. Related to Individual Institutions
III. Financial Records
Collection development (Libraries) -- United States; Libraries -- Special collections -- Religion; Library science -- Societies, etc.; Theological libraries -- United States; Librarians; Morris, Raymond P.; American Theological Library Association; Sealantic Fund, Inc
- Administrative Material, Series I
  - Bulletins, 1961-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Theological Book List (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General LDP Correspondence, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - LDP Correspondence between Raymond Morris and Calvin Schmitt, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - ATLA LDP sample forms (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - ATLA LDP Executive Report, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - ATLA LDP Final Report, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Study Documents of Participating Institutions, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Comparison of library expenses before and after involvement in ATLA LDP, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Related to Individual Institutions, Series II
  - Anderson Theological Seminary, 1964 - 1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Andover-Harvard Theological Library, 1962 - 1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Andover Newton Theological School: General Correspondence, 1961 - 1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Andover Newton Theological School: Visitation Correspondence and Report, 1961 - 1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Asbury Theological Seminary: General Correspondence, 1961 - 1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Asbury Theological Seminary: Reports, 1962 - 1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Austin Presbyterian Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Berkeley Baptist Divinity School, 1961 - 1966 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Berkeley Divinity School, 1961 - 1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Bethany Theological Seminary (formerly Bethany Biblical Seminary), 1962 - 1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bethany Theological Seminary and Northern Baptist Theological Seminary, 1966 - 1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Bethel Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Boston University School of Theology, 1961 - 1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Brite Divinity School, Texas Christian University, 1961 - 1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - California Baptist Theological Seminary, 1962 - 1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Calvin Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1968 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Candler School of Theology, Emory University, 1961 - 1966 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Central Baptist Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Chicago Lutheran Theological Seminary, 1962 - 1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Chicago Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Chicago University Divinity School, 1961 - 1967 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Christian Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Church Divinity School of the Pacific, 1961 - 1966 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Colgate Rochester Divinity School, 1961 - 1967 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Colgate Rochester Divinity School, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - College of the Bible (now Lexington Theological Seminary): General Correspondence, 1961-1966 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - College of the Bible (now Lexington Theological Seminary): Reports, 1961- 1966 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Columbia Theological Seminary, 1961- 1966 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Concordia Seminary, 1963 - 1966 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Crozer Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Crozer Theological Seminary and Lancaster Theological Seminary, 1968 - 1969 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Divinity School of the Protestant Episcopal Church, 1963 - 1966 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Drake University, 1961 - 1966 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Drew Theological School, 1962 - 1966 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Dubuque Theological Seminary, 1962 - 1967 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Dubuque Theological Seminary, 1968 - 1969 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Duke University, 1961 - 1967 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Eastern Baptist Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Eden Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1969 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Emmanuel College, 1961 - 1967 (Box 6, Folder 2,3)
  - Emmanuel School of Religion, Milligan College, 1968 - 1969 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Emory University, see: Candler School of Theology
  - Episcopal Theological School, 1961 - 1969 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Episcopal Theological Seminary of the South-West, 1961 - 1967 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Evangelical Lutheran Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1968 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Evangelical Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Fuller Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1967 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Garrett Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 7, Folder 4, 5)
  - General Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Golden Gate Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1967 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Gordon Divinity School, 1963 - 1966 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Goshen College Biblical Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 8, Folder 2, 3)
  - Hamma Divinity School, 1961 - 1966 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Hartford Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Howard University School of Religion, 1961 - 1966 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Illif School of Theology, 1961 - 1967 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Interdenominational Theological Center, 1961 - 1966 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Knox College, 1961 - 1966 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Lancaster Theological Seminary see also Crozer Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Lexington Theological Seminary, see: College of the Bible
  - Louisville Presbyterian Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1968 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Luther Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1967 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Lutheran School of Theology (formerly Augustana Theological Seminary), 1961 - 1965 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Lutheran School of Theology at Chicago, 1964 - 1967 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Lutheran Theological Seminary, Gettysburg, 1961 - 1968 (Box 9, Folder 5, 6)
  - Lutheran Theological Seminary, Phila., 1961 - 1967 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Lutheran Theological Southern Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - McCormick Theological Seminary, 1962 - 1967 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - McGill University, Faculty of Divinity, 1960 - 1967 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - McMaster Divinity College, 1961 - 1967 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Memphis Theological Seminary, 1967 - 1968 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Mennonite Biblical Seminary, 1964 - 1966 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Methodist Church, Board of Missions, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Methodist Theological School in Ohio, 1963 - 1967 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Midwestern Baptist Theological Seminary, 1964 - 1966 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Milligan College, see: Emmanuel School of Religion
  - Moravian Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Nashotah House, 1961 - 1965 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - New Brunswick Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - New Orleans Baptist Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1968 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - New York Theological Seminary (formerly Biblical Seminary in New York), 1960 - 1966 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - North Park Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Northern Baptist Theological Seminary, see: Bethany Theological Seminary
  - Northwestern Lutheran Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Oberlin Graduate School of Theology, 1961 - 1966 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Pacific Lutheran Theological Seminary, 1964 - 1966 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Pacific School of Religion, 1961 - 1968 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Perkins School of Theology, SMU, 1961 - 1966 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Phillips University, Graduate Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Pittsburgh Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Princeton Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - St. Paul School of Theology, 1963 - 1967 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - San Francisco Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Seabury-Western Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Southeastern Baptist Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1968 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Southern Baptist Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1967 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Southern California School of Theology at Claremont, 1961 - 1969 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Southern Methodist University, see: Perkins School of Theology
  - Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1967 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Texas Christian University, see: Brite Divinity School
  - Union Theological Seminary, New York, 1961 - 1966 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Union Theological Seminary, Richmond, 1962 - 1966 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - United Theological Seminary University of Dubuque, see: Dubuque Theological Seminary, 1962 - 1966 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - University of the South School of Theology, 1961 - 1966 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Vanderbilt Divinity School, 1961 - 1967 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Theological Seminary, 1962 - 1966 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Wartburg Theological Seminary, 1962 - 1967 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Wesley Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1966 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Western Theological Seminary, 1961 - 1967 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Financial Records, Series III
  - Receipts and Acknowledgments for ATLA LDP checks, 1962 - 1967 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Financial Record Books, 1961 - 1973 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1961 - 1973 (Box 15, Folder 3)